So, sometimes you've talked about
the practice of not giving things center
stage. I'm just wondering um
I'm just wondering um
what would be kind of a practical way of
thinking about that if it sounds
abstract um and how you'd actually put it into
um and how you'd actually put it into
practice.
Well, it it refers to the things
that are kind of pressuring you towards
um
taking up the center stage, towards
taking up
all of your uh attention
and the span. So, um
the beginning of not giving the center
stage is comes down to
um
making the right choices in terms of
centrality, ill will, and distraction.
So, if say you have a central desire that
if say you have a central desire that
you consciously recognize and you
recognize that you could
go along
with the pressure,
with less resistance, or say no to it.
Uh saying no to it is already not giving
the center stage.
So, if if you train in that in regard to
the last and ill will,
um
hindrances in general,
then you can start to discern these um
subtler acceptances
of those uh states,
uh states of mind or on the mental
level.
So, by that um
kind of what I mean is like you you you
can't be practicing not giving the
center stage mentally if you would have
already physically chosen to act out of
ill will or sloth and torpor or five
hindrances, sensuality, and so on.
So, that's how you practically go about
it. You recognize that
um cheetah, the animal, wants to pull
you in the direction it wants to go, which
in the direction it wants to go, which
is the center stage, figuratively
speaking. Um so, putting brakes on that, building
Um so, putting brakes on that, building
up a certain um
like a like a buffer zone, a certain
sort of
perim- perimeter of containment,
enduring it on the right level, all of
those are other ways of different ways
of saying like not giving it the center
stage it wants.
So, it's kind of important to recognize
that this is inseparable from
the lifestyle and lifestyle choices that
pertain to the body and speech
cuz obviously people can think of can
hear this, can hear about, you know,
peripheral awareness and yoniso
manasikara, and think that they can just do that on
and think that they can just do that on
top of the
um
animal that's still allowed to act
physically, verbally, uh and it's like,
"No, that's just going to remain
abstraction." They will obviously then
confuse a person in believing that
they're actually practicing on the right
level when they are not.
But say you do train
physically, you say no to things you
should say no to,
you don't follow the desires blindly,
you don't act out of ill will, you
endure things on the right level, then
you will recognize when these
uh pressures present themselves
to say something unwholesome, to do
something unwholesome, to think
something unwholesome.
And you recognize, "Okay, so I can't
remove these images from my mind. I
can't remove these thoughts that
presented themselves,
but I can certainly unfocus from them to
put it away.
Like I I don't have to allow them to
occupy the center and give them my
attention in that sense."
So, that's like not giving it the center
stage on that subtler mental level. So,
and I said it before, you know, like you
don't need to start thinking about
central thoughts to know that your mind
is inclined sensually.
You don't have to start thinking about
specific people you don't like and ill will and
people you don't like and ill will and
anger and hatred to know that your mind
is angry or hateful.
Because you already know the state of
the mind, and as a matter of fact, you
know that if you were to give the center
stage, you know you know uh what thoughts would
you know you know uh what thoughts would
crystallize as a result of it.
You know that. You don't need to
crystallize them to know what you you
already know. If I were to allow this, I
know exactly what direction my thoughts
will take
in terms of sensuality or ill will and
so on. So, that's what I mean, like by
not allowing that, you're not allowing
that center stage to to to grow and
fester and proliferate and increase its
its its strength and momentum.
So, you could have it at the back of
your mind, say a
a an a nagging ill will,
and you see that, you recognize it
really as such. You don't act out of it
physically, and then you know, I'm not
going to stop doing whatever I'm doing
in order to think about this cuz I know
exactly where those thoughts will go. If they
where those thoughts will go. If they
take up that ill will
that's at the back of my mind, I know
exactly what those thoughts will
crystallize into.
So, you don't do it. You actually
abstain from it.
That's how you know when the suttas
describe purifying thoughts in their
arising. In other words, seeing the the basin
In other words, seeing the the basin
from which those thoughts appear and
recognizing it already as mind affected
with ill will or mind not affected with
ill will.
Chitta affected with lust or chitta not
affected with lust, and so on.
And so, you you were saying that just
keeping precepts, just training in sense
restraint and whatnot is already
preventing you it's already it already
implies you're keeping things off of
center stage to a certain extent.
>> To a degree.
Is that because like take um
just sensuality for instance. If you
take on celibacy, Mhm. it seems like if
you really want to like solidify
yourself in being celibate, you have to
learn to cut things off sooner. Mhm.
Like it's not just you let things go all
the way until they get right to a
certain point.
You want
>> You mean mentally? Yeah, like mentally,
like just the kind of like celibacy is
not just constantly like surely
resisting the already built up
>> Of course not. No.
>> Yeah. So, to an extent you would have to
learn this.
>> you would not be able to cut things off
mentally on the level of such decision
on the level of such decision
if physically you are not already
withdrawn withdrawn from those things.
So, physical withdrawal is already implied.
physical withdrawal is already implied.
In and of itself, yes, it's not going to
automatically or magically result in
purification. You could live physically
withdrawn, but if you don't make the
effort to say mentally understand the danger,
to say mentally understand the danger,
the peril of those thoughts to through
not allowing them the center stage where
they occupy all of they take over the
context, basically,
take over the reins, then it's like then
yeah, you're not going to you're not
going to be free from it.
But you would be nowhere even in a
position of deciding to not go back to
sensuality or to refrain from doing so
or not act out of ill will if you're
already not to some degree developed
ability to physically say no to those
things. So, he he he has to start from the
So, he he he has to start from the
bottom up. Yeah.
It's not like, "Oh, until I'm physically
perfect, I shall not even think about
mentally making effort." No, of course.
It's it's it's you know, it's like a one
thing kind of develops the other,
but there is a certain order to to like,
you know, you could be making all the
mental effort you want if physically
you're still sitting in the water,
you're not going to be drying yourself
up at all.
Um so so that's that's kind of the
recognition, which I yeah, I guess it is
useful because sometimes people would
take even the eight precepts in that
blind manner,
whereby I'll just blindly adhere to
this, not make any effort to mentally,
you know, discern the danger, the center
stage, where my mind leans to, what it
prefers, what it doesn't prefer, and so on, and
what it doesn't prefer, and so on, and
I'll just all of that will magically
resolve itself simply by me
uh adhering to these uh eight
commandments or something, but it won't.
It it provides a basis for potential
development, but if the effort is not invested
but if the effort is not invested
towards that development, it won't
occur. Yeah.